Guide to the Noyes Family Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Noyes family papers
1851-1922
MS 851
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1.5
Correspondence, printed matter, and memorabilia of Atherton Noyes (1862-1938) and his brother Edward Parish Noyes (1857-1913). Material concerns the undergraduate years of his brothers at Yale, classes of 1880 and 1885, Atherton Noyes' life in Colorado, and his trip to Europe in 1894-1895.
Noyes family
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchase and gift from Leroy E. Wilson, 1976.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The Noyes Family Papers consist of correspondence, memorabilia, and printed matter relating to Atherton and Edward Parish Noyes and their families. The bulk of the papers is made up of letters written by the brothers to each other and to other family members and friends. Included is correspondence from their years at Yale University (Edward was a member of the class of 1880, Atherton of the class of 1885) and their later lives; in particular there are numerous letters from Atherton describing his life in Colorado from 1887 on, and his visit to Europe in 1894-1895. As well as correspondence, the papers contain a good deal of Yale memorabilia and some other printed matter, and several photographs of Atherton.
The papers of the two brothers have beenseparated, and their correspondence arranged chronologically. Letters between the two are filed under the author's name. These papers were acquired by Yale University by purchase and gift from LeRoy E. Wilson in 1976.
Biographical / Historical
Atherton Noyes, B.A. 1885.
Born June 14, 1862, in New York City.
Died November 19, 1938, in Cambridge, Mass.
Father, Rev. Daniel Parker Noyes, '40. Mother, Helen McGregor (Means) Noyes. Yale relatives include: Edward P. Noyes, '80 (brother); Frederic Adams, '62, and D. McGregor Means, '68 (cousins).
Phillips-Andover. Oration appointment Junior year; dissertation appointment Senior year; member Dunham Boat Club three years; Class tennis club Junior year; teacher at Temple Street Mission School Senior year; member Debating Club, Ivy Committee, Gamma Nu, and Psi Upsilon.
Private tutor New York City 1885-86; attended Harvard Medical School 1886-87; because of ill-health went to Colorado in 1887 and until 1892 had no regular occupation other than being in banking business in Aspen, Colo., for a short time and in real estate business in Colorado Springs; secretary Colorado Summer School 1892-93 and director 1896; teacher in Cutler Academy; instruction in English Colorado College 1893-99 and in Greek 1894-99, assistant professor of English 1899-1913 and of Greek 1899-1903, professor of English 1913-18, and dean of the faculty 1895-1901; exchange professor at Harvard 1915-16; instructor in English Harvard 1919-25 and Radcliffe 1918-28; retired in 1928 and had since resided in Cambridge; author: Matthew Arnold's Poetry; an Appreciation (1916) and "Katharsis in Literature and Life," ( Sewanee Review, October, 1921); M.A. Harvard 1916; member Archaeological Institute and First Church (Congregational), Boston, Mass.
Married July 10, 1901, in Intervale, N.H., Margaret Davenport, daughter of William Eliot and Eliza Heyer (Polhemus) Fette. Children: Atherton, Jr. (B.A. Harvard 1926, M.A. 1928, M.S. 1929, S.D. 1934); Marion MacGregor (died June 21, 1906); Eliot Fette (B.A. Harvard 1932, M.Arch. 1938); and Margaret (B.A. Radcliffe 1934).
Death due to bronchopneumonia and carcinoma. Buried in Mount Auburn Cemetery, Cambridge. Survived by wife, two sons, daughter, and two grandchildren.
(Taken from Yale University Obituary Record ).
* * * * *
Edward Parish Noyes
Son of Rev. Daniel Parker Noyes (B.A. Yale 1840), Tutor in Yale College from 1843 to 1847, and Helen McGregor (Means) Noyes, was born September 26, 1857, in New York City, where his father was then secretary of the American (now Congregational) Home Missionary Society. During his boyhood he also lived at Orange, N. J., and Brookline and Rockport, Mass. He was prepared for college at Phillips Academy, Andover, Mass.
After graduation he learned the machinist's trade in the Lowell (Mass.) Machine Shops, studying especially the construction of cotton machinery. He spent considerable time for the company in the South superintending the equipment of cotton mills, especially in South Carolina and Tennessee, continuing this line of work until 1884, when he entered the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, and took a special one-year course. For nine years following he was connected with the Neverslip Horseshoe Co. of Boston, and after that was treasurer of the Hancock Inspirator Co. until July, 1896. Since then he had been an expert in mechanical engineering, his office being in Boston and his residence since 1892 in Winchester.
Mr. Noyes died suddenly of heart trouble at his home in Winchester, September 20, 1913, in the 56th year of his age.
He married, November 7, 1891, in Hastings, England, Jessie Porter Hill, daughter of Richard and Harriet (Winter) Hill, of Davenport, Ia. She died July 22, 1897, but two daughters and a son survived him. A brother (B.A. Yale 1885) is Assistant Professor of English in Colorado College.
(Taken from Yale University Obituary Record ).
Families; Colorado -- Social life and customs; Europe -- Description and travel; Businessmen; Educators; Noyes, Atherton, 1862-1938; Noyes, Daniel; Noyes, Edward Parish, 1857-1913; Noyes family; Yale University -- Students
- Inventory
  - Atherton Noyes
    - Outgoing correspondence, 1881-1922, undated (Box 1, Folder 1 - 32)
    - Incoming correspondence, 1881-1884, undated (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Scrapbook of Yale memorabilia, 1881-1885 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Loose papers removed from scrapbook, 1881-1885 (Box 2, Folder 35 - 36)
    - Photographs, 1880, undated (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Edward Parish Noyes
    - Outgoing correspondence, 1875-1913, undated (Box 3, Folder 38 - 60)
    - Incoming correspondence, 1881-1887, undated (Box 3, Folder 61)
    - Yale memorabilia, 1878-1890, undated (Box 3, Folder 62)
  - Correspondence of other family members, 1851-1906, undated (Box 3, Folder 63)
  - Yale printed matter, 1876-1886, undated (Box 3, Folder 64)
  - Other printed matter, 1888-1920, undated (Box 3, Folder 65)